that I blew the whistle on the CIA's
torture program in a nationally
televised interview with ABC News. The
second reason is
I blew the whistle a long time ago and
just in the past 18 months I seem to
have hit some sort of YouTube algorithm
sweet spot and all of a sudden my
message is getting out there.
>> And you went to prison for blowing the
whistle. I did and I would do it again
tomorrow. I really would. You know, I
was I was giving an interview to the BBC
the day after I got out of prison. They
were the first uh outlet to ask for an
interview. And so I gladly gave it to
them. And the interviewer said
kind of perturbedly,
"You're not showing any remorse or
contrition." And I said, "No, I'm not
remorseful. I'm not contrite. I would do
it again. I would let them send me to
prison again because it was the right
thing to do.
>> And you were a spy in the CIA.
>> Yeah, I was quite an accomplished spy in
the CIA. I spent 15 years in the CIA.
The first half of my career was in
analysis and uh and I got bored,
frankly. And so I made an unusual at the
time change to counterterrorism
operations. And then I was the chief of
CIA counterterrorism operations in
Pakistan after the 9/11 attacks.
>> And if I'd never heard about the CIA
before and I had never heard about your
role in the CIA before and I was a
16-year-old,
>> right?
>> How would you explain to me what you did
there, what your role was and what the
CIA is?
>> Sure. The CIA is an intelligence service
whose job it is at its most basic level
to recruit spies to steal secrets and to
analyze those secrets so that the
policymakers can make the best informed
policy. After 9/11, we were expecting an
attack, to use Osama bin Laden's words,
that would dwarf 911.
And so my job was to infiltrate al-Qaeda
by recruiting members of al-Qaeda
to tell us when and where that next
attack was going to come so that we
could disrupt it. We could
kill or capture the leadership and
destroy the organization.
>> And give me a range of the things that
you did during your time in the CIA just
for a very topline range of the types of
things you worked on. Oh, sure. Um, as
an analyst, it was actually quite
straightforward. Uh, we would write for
the president, the vice president, the
secretaries of state and defense, and
the national security adviser.
>> And who were the presidents during that
time?
>> Uh, when I started, it was George HW
Bush, the father, and then it was Bill
Clinton, then George W. Bush. There are
several different publications. There's
the president's daily brief, which is
the most important. I covered Iraq the
entire time that I was in analysis from
well before most Americans had ever
heard of Iraq. I was told actually that
it was a training account because
nothing ever happened there. Nothing
ever changed. And then Iraq invaded
Kuwait. The next day I got to the office
early. I was 25
years old, 26 years old. And uh my boss
said, "Don't take your jacket off. We're
going to the White House." I had never
been to the White House before except as
a tourist. And so we got in a car, went
to the White House. We're ushered into
the Oval Office. It's the president, the
vice president, the national security
adviser, the director of the CIA, my
boss, and me. And then we all sit down.
The president tells us, "Sit down." We
sit down and the president says,"Well,
now what do we do?" And everybody turns
and looks at me. And it took me a
second. And I said, "Uh, yes." I said,
"Mr. President, as you know, Iraqi
troops crossed the border at 2:00 this
morning. They the royal family has uh
has run away to uh Saudi Arabia. They've
named a new occupation governor, etc.,
etc. Do we know who that is?" I said,
"Yes, sir." I gave him the name and I
said, "Actually, he uh he's the
co-founder of the Popular Front for the
Liberation of Palestine." The vice
president shouts, "Jesus Christ." And
then the president says, "Gentlemen,
thank you. Thank you. We'll take it from
here." And I remember saying to myself,
"My friends would never believe in a
thousand years what I was doing right
now. They wouldn't even believe me if I
told them." That's what an analyst does.
When I switched to operations again, the
the job was very straightforward. It was
to recruit spies to steal secrets. But
then if you're involved in
counterterrorism operations, there are a
lot of extras that you have to be
trained in. So you go through the normal
spy training. This is how you ingratiate
yourself. It's something called the
asset acquisition cycle. Spot, assess,
develop, recruit. I meet you at a
cocktail party. You seem like a nice
guy. I introduce myself.
I ask, "Uh, so what do you do for a
living?" Well, if you tell me you manage
a shoe store, I'm going to say, "Well,
it was very nice meeting you," and I'm
going to go on to the next guy. But if
you tell me you work at the port, you
work in the Ministry of Defense, you
work in the Chinese embassy,
I'm going to invite you to lunch. I've
spotted you. I've assessed you. And my
assessment is I'd like to get to know
you. Then I begin to develop you. I'll
give you an example. I was in Pakistan.
I got a tip that uh that al-Qaeda, a
group of mid-level al-Qaeda fighters was
meeting every single day in a coffee
shop at 10:00 in the morning. My Arabic
was absolutely flawless at the time. And
so I had a bushy beard that I grew for
operational reasons.
>> Can I hear some of your Arabic?
>> Yeah.
It's nice to meet you. Or
Alhamdulillah.
Uh, so I uh I bought an Arabic newspaper
and I went to the coffee shop and I just
sat there and sure enough at 10:00 the
four of them came in. One of them looked
at me and I looked at him and that was
it. We made eye contact. I did that for
a week.
The second week I was there drinking my
coffee, sitting with my Arabic
newspaper, and the one who had looked at
me the week before, he nodded. So I
nodded back. That was it. No
communication otherwise. The third week,
I'm a regular now. He recognizes me.
So he says to me, "Salamlaykum." I said,
"Walaykum salsalam. May peace be upon
you." And I say, "And upon you peace."
One day he came in alone. And I said,
"Please have a seat. Sit with me. No
sense in you sitting alone and me
sitting alone." So he sat down. We
started talking. And um I asked him how
long he had been in Pakistan. He said,
"Oh, I've been here for 5 years. I was
in Afghanistan. I was making jihad
against the Americans." And I said, "Oh,
that must have been hell on earth." He
said, "Oh." He said that the bombing of
Tora was hideous. That was the word that
he used. It was hideous. And I said,
"And what about your family? How's your
family?" He said, "My wife and and son
and daughter are in Cairo. I've never
met my son. He was born just after I
left to make jihad." I said, "I'm so
sorry." And he said, "Yes, I'm I'm
lonely and I I want to go home." And we
continued this relationship. And
finally, I said to him, "Let me take you
to dinner. Let's get out of the coffee
shop." The truth was I didn't want one
of his friends to walk in and see us.
So, we went to a restaurant for dinner
and I said, "Listen,
there's something that I haven't been
truthful with you about.
I'm not Lebanese."
And I said, "Actually, I'm American. Are
you okay with that?"
And he says, "I think so." I said,
'Well, actually,
I'm a CIA officer.
And he says,"Okay."
So, he didn't run screaming from the
room or pull a gun or anything. And he
said,
"Why do you want me? Why do you want to
talk to me?" I said, "Actually, you have
access to something that I want." It was
very specific. And I told him what it
was. And he says, "And what will you do
for me?" And I said, "Anything your
heart desires."
And he said, "I want to go home."
I said, "I can do that."
>> You wanted information presumably.
>> I wanted information. Very specific
information
>> which you can't share.
>> No. Now go right back to prison. So uh
[laughter]
so um we got him a passport. I bought
him a first class ticket
and I took him to the airport. gave him
some cash to get himself started again.
And I said, "Before you go, I have to
ask you, why did you agree to give me
this information? I mean, presumably I'm
the enemy." And he said, "I've been here
5 years, and you're the first person who
ever asked me about my family."
So I said, "Best of luck. Never saw him
again."
That's the job
>> I have to ask you.
>> Mhm.
Take me on the journey of you being a
young man
>> in West Pennsylvania,
>> right,
>> to becoming a spy. What happened?
Because I'll be I'll be honest, you
know, I don't really know what my
perception of spies is, but it's not
you.
>> That's good.
>> Yeah,
>> that's good. See, because I kind of work
under the radar. M so that's really
interesting is I [laughter] there's
there's so many um once you learn about
spies as a podcast like so if you go
back a couple of years and someone had
told me about spies I wouldn't have
believed them I wouldn't have believed
that these things actually happened. Oh
yeah.
>> You know, you hear about people going
undercover
>> and going to other countries and getting
secrets and and all of these things.
>> And it's not until you meet the people
that said,
"Yes, that's me. I used to do that."
That you're sort of you have this
paradigm shift in your mind and you go,
"Oh my god, what else might be going
on?"
>> Right?
>> Because I lived in this world probably
up until the age of, I don't know, 30
years old where I kind of just assume
things are what they are
>> like as I see them. And then, you know,
you start to discover that there's
layers of secrecy. Nations are against
each other. They're doing all of these
covert operations.
>> And even like as a podcaster now, I have
moments where I go
like, "How do I know that you're not
you're not here to steal secrets from
me?"
>> Right?
>> So, you know what's funny? When I had
Andrew Bustamante on the show, the
comment sections are always the same.
They're always like, "Once a CIA spy,
always a CIA spy."
>> I hate when people say that. It's so
intellectually lazy.
>> But I just I do wonder and I go, "Okay,
here's a super conspiracy theory. What
if the CIA have made spies do really
well in the YouTube algorithm so that
all of us as long form podcasters invite
them on and then they
>> You know what? I would agree with that.
I would have agreed with that a year ago
because Andrew Bamante has really made a
handsome living out of selling his
experience and he's on every podcast.
>> Yeah. But I am the most anti-CIA former
CIA person that's out there.
>> But wouldn't that be the perfect CIA
agent?
>> I mean, if if I weren't constantly
criticizing the CIA as a as a an
organization that's just out of control.
>> Do you think the CIA are have a strategy
for podcasters and for podcasting?
>> I think yes, now they do. It took them a
little while to to get current, but just
like they over time developed a strategy
with Hollywood, sure, they're developing
a strategy with podcasters. You know, it
was only in the last 10 years that the
CIA opened a branch within the Office of
Public Affairs whose job it is solely to
lies with Hollywood studios. The FBI's
been doing this since the since the 40s.
And the goal is that everything that
comes out of Hollywood should be pro-
CIA and you know we end up with with
Zero Dark 30 and you know the recruit
and the CIA Argo the CIA is always the
hero in these movies.
>> If you were still at the CIA now and
your job was to in infiltrate and
uh use creators or podcasters as an
asset for the CIA's objectives. How
might you design that plan? If we were
just hypothesizing,
you would have to have
a goal
that would be specific enough that you
could actually track the progress to it.
So, you can't just say, "Well, I'm gonna
pay this podcaster x amount of money,
and we're gonna we're gonna we're gonna
do something with the algorithm to make
him vastly popular among
men, you know, 18 to 30, let's say.
There's got to be more to it than that.
It has to be a message. You've got to be
able to get a specific, well-honed
message out there. And the message can
be anything.
It could be, you know, love the CIA.
We're the good guys. It could be support
the overthrow of the Iranian government.
It could be, you know, any criticism of
Benjamin Netanyahu is anti-semitism.
It could be anything you want it to be.
You just have to make sure that it's
repeated enough. See, this was the
danger with the torture program. This is
one of the very important reasons that I
went public when I did because my
colleagues, my superiors at the CIA kept
repeating this lie over and over and
over again that torture worked and that
torture got us information that saved
American lives. And that was just simply
not true. It was a lie. Besides being
illegal, immoral, unethical, it just
wasn't true. And so I decided before we
go down this road anymore, I'm going to
go public.
>> So can you take me back then? We got a
little bit sidetracked there, but
>> Sure.
>> John, how did you come to be a CIA spy?
>> When I was 9 years old, I told my
parents that I wanted to be a spy when I
grew up. it came time to apply for
college and I only applied at one
university, George Washington University
in Washington because it was two blocks
from the White House and it was one of
only three schools in America that
offered a Middle Eastern studies
program. I was one of only four people
in that brand new Middle Eastern studies
program. I stayed for a master's degree
in legislative affairs with a focus on
foreign policy analysis. I was taking a
class in that program called the
psychology of leadership. It was taught
by an eminent psychiatrist named Dr.
Gerald Post and he gave us an assignment
one uh one day where we had to shadow
our bosses. We had to just follow our
bosses for a week.
>> Your bosses?
>> Yeah. I worked at a labor union called
the United Food and Commercial Workers
Union. And so we were just supposed to
follow our boss around for a week and
then write a psychological profile. I
used dozens of, you know, footnotes from
psychological, you know, psychology
texts and I ended up saying that he was
a sociopath with psychopathic and
possibly violent tendencies and, you
know, I had these citations.
I passed the paper in. Dr. Post gives it
back to me a week later, gave me an A,
and then he wrote, "Please see me after
class." So I went up to him after the
class and I said, "Dr. Post, you wanted
to see me." He says, "Come to my
office." So we went down there. He
closed the door and he says, "Listen,
I'm not really a professor here. I'm a
CIA officer undercover as a professor
here, and I'm looking for people who
would fit into the CIA's culture. I
think you would fit into the CIA's
culture. Would you like to be a spy?
And I said, "Yes,
I would." He picked up the phone and
called a number and he said, "Bob, this
is Jerry. I've got a good one for you.
Do you have some time?" And he said,
"Sure." He writes an address on a scrap
of paper and he says, "Be at this
address in 20 minutes." It was only one
subway stop away. So, I jumped on the
metro. I went to Rosland, Virginia, just
across the river. I had to buzz to be
led in. And a woman opens the door. She
says, "Are you here for Bob?" And I
said, "Yes." She says, "Come on in."
I'm sitting there for a moment and then
this like 6'6,
350 lb giant barrels out of his office
and he says, "John Bob, how the hell are
you? I want you to be at the George
Washington University Medical School
Saturday morning at 8:00. We've got some
tests for you. I said, "Okay." And then
we shook hands and I left. So Saturday
morning, I went to the GW Medical School
auditorium. There were like I don't know
200 people there and they hand us a
test. My wife picked me up. She said,
"How did you do?" I said, "I have no
idea."
>> Does your wife at this point know that
you're applying for the CIA?
>> Yes. And that was going to be pretty
much the extent of what she ended up
knowing cuz once I got in.
>> But you weren't allowed to tell her.
>> I was not allowed to tell her. No.
>> So you told her anyway?
>> Yeah. When I first applied, they said,
"Listen, don't tell anybody because you
may go under cover. You may go under
deep cover. And we can't have people out
there who know that you're a CIA
officer."
>> Presumably, the CIA is smart enough to
be able to check if you've told her.
Yeah. And they ask you on the polygraph,
"Did you tell her?"
>> Really?
>> And I said, "Yeah, I told her." She's my
wife. What am I going to do? You know,
but it got to the point where I'd get
home from a day where, you know, I broke
into some guy's house and and planted a
camera on a bug. And I'd get home and
she'd say, "How was your day?" I'd say,
"Great. What'd you do?" Not a darn
thing. And then my phone would ring at,
you know, midnight and a guy would say,
"The rain in Spain falls mainly in the
plane." And I'd say uh Marzy dots and
dozy dots and little lambs Ivy and that
means meet me at the yacht club parking
lot in three hours.
And then I'd leave. She's she would say,
"Where are you going? It's midnight. I
got to work." So I'd leave. I'd do my
meeting. I'd come home 6:00 in the
morning just in time to shower and shave
and get dressed to go to work. And she
would say, "What was her name?"
And I I remember this one terrible time.
That's what she said to me. What was her
name? The truth is I had been sitting in
a garbage dumpster waiting for a guy to
drive by down the alley and throw a bag
of documents in. And I stunk of garbage.
And I said to her, "Do I seriously smell
to you like I've been with a woman?"
Seriously.
So we ended up getting a divorce.
[laughter]
>> [gasps]
>> So you do the assessment presumably you
get in the training he he called me like
two weeks later Bob did and he said you
blew the doors off those tests. I said
oh great okay so a month later they
summoned me to headquarters
and uh I was interviewed by the office
of neareastern operations, the office of
neareastern analysis and the office of
leadership analysis. I was offered the
analysis job on the Iraq desk.